Hey there. Uh in this particular
session, we are going to talk about test
configuration. And then uh we'll talk
about how to configure your tests in
Tosca and what are test configuration
parameters, uh where you can set this
configuration parameters.
And then uh what types of configuration
parameters are present in Tosca.
But first, uh let's try to understand uh
what is test configuration. And then why
do you need it? So, in any automation
framework or any automation tool you're
using, if you're building some
automation tests, then you want to uh
run that automation tests multiple times
with different set of values. For
example, if uh you are running your
tests in a particular environment, uh
which has got a URL, right? And then uh
you want to run the same test with a
different URL the second time around.
So, you have to go back and either
change your test uh value right in your
script or what you can do is you can
create a configuration parameter and
then use that parameter in your test so
that you don't need to change the value
uh at different places in your test
script, right? That will only increase
uh your test development time. Also, it
will increase your maintenance time when
uh any of the tests uh which you have
developed fail. So, to make this uh
easier and also less time-consuming, uh
we generally configure our tests. So,
every test framework uh has got some
level of uh configurable values.
And these values could be used uh in
your test scripts so that they could be
developed uh much faster also they could
be maintained easily.
Now, um in Tosca, uh we can configure
our tests using the test configuration
parameters. So, we can set values uh for
these parameters, and then we can use
them in our tests.
Now, these configuration parameters uh
can be set for different Tosca objects,
right from the root element uh to
component folders, to configuration
folders, to test cases, executions,
uh and even the test case design folder,
right? So, everywhere you will find a
tab, which is the test configuration.
So, when you go into the project root
element, you will see there is a
configuration tab.
And then uh the same uh you will find
for the test cases,
and the same you'll find for execution,
and also for test case design, right?
So, all of these places you can create
this uh test configuration parameters.
And then uh these configuration
parameters, some of them are defined by
the system, which is Tosca, and uh
others you can define on your own. You
can create your own custom configuration
values, which you want to use in your
test cases.
So, now uh let's talk about uh
what are these test configuration
parameters, uh and what are the types of
test configuration parameters, which are
available in Tosca,
and uh how can you use them to create uh
different parameters, which can be used
at different places in your test
scripts.
Now, although there are a lot of test
configuration parameters, uh and the
whole list is available on the Tosca uh
support documentation, but I've listed
down some of the important ones, uh
which you might come across uh while you
are doing script development.
Now, these are also divided across
different engines like the X browser
engine,
uh the T-Box engine, and the mobile
engine. And uh depending on which type
of test cases you are creating, we'll be
using these parameters, right? So,
generally for web applications, we will
be using the X browser engine. And the
most common type of parameter uh we will
use is the browser parameter.
Now, uh this browser parameter uh has
got some default uh
browser values which you can use. So, it
has got a list of all the different
values uh which can be used, right? From
Chrome, Firefox, Edge, Internet
Explorer, and uh the list keeps on
increasing, right? So, you can use uh
any browser value in this particular
parameter, and then uh your test will be
made configurable because you can run it
in any particular browser, right?
So, similarly, you can also set the
browser version.
And then we have got two other
parameters which are related to
accessibility. So, one uh is whether you
want to run the accessibility analysis,
and one is if you want to run it in the
fast mode, right? So, these are some of
the parameters for the X browser engine.
Then um
when we are using the T-Box modules, uh
we will also use some of the parameters.
And these are some of the parameters.
So, we have got the avoid execution
recorder.
Now, this will help you to either enable
or disable uh the recording for a
particular test case, right?
Then we have got different configuration
parameters for the recovery engine.
Um so, we can set uh the values here for
uh the on dialog failure, on exception
failure, or on verification failure,
what you want uh Tosca to do, right? So,
you can set that configuration here.
Then uh we have got the page sync
parameter.
Now, this page sync parameter, it is
basically used uh uh for uh
uh different Ajax requests, right? So,
if you don't want to continue with test
execution, then you can set this to
true.
Then uh we have got the scrolling
behavior. So, using this uh you can tell
Tosca whether you want to scroll uh a
vertical or horizontal.
We have got the synchronization timeout.
Now, you can set uh the timeout value
for uh synchronizing your elements uh
with Tosca. So, it will have a default
value, but then you can change this in
your configuration parameter.
Then uh we have got uh the target date
format, and similarly we have got target
time format. So, you can set a
particular format which you want to use
for your particular tests if you set
that parameter value.
Then uh we have got the test step
retries. Now, this will uh define how
many times you want to retry a
particular step. So, that you can define
in this particular parameter.
Similarly, we have got the test case
retries. Uh these are all part of the
recovery engine.
Then we have got some parameters which
are specific to the mobile engine.
And this will be separately covered uh
in the mobile uh sessions.
But uh we have got the APM server. We we
can set the browser. We can set the
device model, device name.
Uh we can also set whether uh we want to
enable the live view.
Uh we can also set whether uh it's an
APM or it's a simulator, right? So, all
these parameters can be used in your
mobile engine test cases.
So, these are some of the different
parameters. Now, if you want to look at
the whole list, uh you can get it uh in
the documentation,
uh which I'm going to provide the link
to.
Now, let's look at a very simple example
on how we can create a test
configuration parameter and how it can
be useful while creating your test cases
for particular test scenarios.
So, uh let's create a test case here.
And let's call this
uh parameters.
So, uh here um I'm just picking up an
example, this particular website, right?
So, what I'm going to do is I am going
to add a test step here.
Um and then we'll say navigate or
uh we'll say open URL.
Okay, and then I'm going to enter the
URL here, so it is going to open this
particular website using this particular
test case.
Okay, and then uh we want to enter the
username and password, right? So, let's
go ahead and scan this quickly.
Okay, so here uh I just need the
username, uh password, and uh the login
button. Uh I've already checked all
these three are unique, so I don't need
to make any changes here.
I'll just go ahead and save this, and uh
I'm going to close it.
Okay, so this is the module uh which you
can see here, and now we can go and drag
it here.
We can add it to our test case, so this
is our second step.
And this is our login step, right?
So, here uh we can use the username. Uh
it's provided here.
So, we'll go back here and put it here.
And then password is here, so we'll
again use the password.
And then for button we will use click,
right?
Now, this test case works fine uh when
you execute it any number of times, but
uh in a scenario where you have to test
multiple scenarios for this particular
page, like uh we have to test with
different usernames, like we have to
test with logged out user, problem user,
performance error, visual, right? So,
there are seven different types of
usernames here, and every particular
username has got a different
functionality, which we need to verify
through automation. So, uh basically,
you need to run this uh test for seven
different test scenarios, right? Or you
need to run this seven times with
different values.
Now, one way is you can create different
tests, uh like you can create seven
tests which has got different uh
usernames, but then you need to execute
it separately, and also you need to
maintain them separately, right? So, the
creation or the development time is
more, and the maintenance time is also
more. And to reduce this, we can use
configuration parameters, right? So, we
can use the configuration parameter for
username.
Probably, we don't need it for password,
because this is not changing, but we can
still have it. And then uh for URL, if
you want to test this particular test
case in different uh environments, like
if this is the test environment, we can
have multiple test environments, right?
So, uh the URLs might be changing. URL
is probably also test configuration
parameter. So, all of these are
different examples of test configuration
parameter. So, instead of using static
values in your test steps, you should be
using parameters wherever you think that
these values uh could change, or you
could run them with different values.
So, the other uh parameter which you can
create is for a browser because
you need to first launch a browser after
that only you can open any particular
URL.
So, the most important configuration
parameter for your web test is the
browser, right?
So, now let's look at how we can create
a test configuration parameter at a test
case level. It is almost the same at any
particular level, okay?
So,
you have to go into the test
configuration tab from the details tab.
And from here we need to right click on
the main test case. There you'll find an
option to create a test configuration
parameter.
So, once you do this, you will see there
is a drop down for the parameter. So,
you can choose the default parameters
here which are defined by Tosca, or you
can choose your own or you can define
your own parameter, right?
So, here I'm going to choose the browser
parameter. And then once you choose
that, you'll see a drop down of values
with all the different browsers, right?
So, I can choose any browser here.
I will go with the Chrome browser.
So, that's one test configuration
parameter which we just defined for this
particular test case.
Similarly, we can create for username.
So, these are all the custom
configuration parameters. These are not
defined by Tosca, right?
And then we can also use URL.
And then we can also add for password.
So, these are the four different
parameters which I can
create for this particular test case.
Now, depending on the test steps, there
could be a number of different
parameters, right?
So, we need to just replace the values
here
for each of these parameters.
So, I can just copy it from here and I
can directly put it here.
And for password, I can take it right
from here.
And then I can paste it here, right? So,
I can change the data type as well. So,
if you're using a password, you can
change it to
password data type so that it is hidden.
And then we can
just replace this actual values
with a particular syntax, okay? So, in
Tosca, we use configuration parameter.
So, we have to use the curly brace and
then curly then CP, which is stands for
configuration parameter.
And then uh once you do that, uh it will
populate all the parameters which are
defined for this particular test case.
So, I can go ahead and use them now.
Okay, and then here, similarly, I can
use the username.
And for password,
uh I can change the data type to string.
And then I can use
password.
Now, uh
what it also does is uh it not only
makes your test configurable, but uh it
also makes it more secure
and also abstract, right? So, now the
test is abstracted for a particular user
who is trying to look at this particular
test steps and just trying to execute it
uh because he'll be only able to see
these uh configuration parameters which
are defined here, but not the actual
values, right? Those values are here in
the test configuration.
Now, whenever these values change, you
don't need to change them in the test
case or test steps, right? So, if these
are used multiple times in a test step
or test case, then um all of these are
referring to these parameters, and we
can change the values here. So, it will
be directly reflecting in your test
steps. Right?
So, consider if you have got 1,000 test
steps which are using the same values,
you don't need to change these values
1,000 times. Right? So, it is saving a
lot of time and effort in order to uh
configure and maintain your test steps.
Now, the other thing uh which you need
to remember when you're working with
test configuration parameter
is you cannot delete any particular
value if you want to. Right? So, there
is no option to delete this.
But, if you want to uh
just change or delete this particular
value, you have to use this option reset
to default value. Okay? So, once you do
that, it will be removed from this
particular list.
So, this is how you can create any test
configuration parameter, and you can
also uh remove them or reset them uh if
you don't want to use them.
And then you can replace the values in
your test steps with those test
configuration parameters. Now, uh the
other thing which you can do is also uh
you can create configurations at a
project level. Right? So, if you have
got this particular project which I have
got, the training project. Now, inside
this uh if I've got multiple projects,
right? Which are using the same
configurations, then I have got a
different section called configurations.
And this is where I can create project
level um configurations. Right?
So, let's see how we can do that.
Um so, here I can create uh a new
configuration. As you can see, there are
some default ones like the API, mobile,
test data service.
Um so, I I create my own configuration.
right?
So, it helps you to structure your test
configuration parameters from a specific
point in your repository, right? So, if
you've got different teams with
different requirements, um then you can
maintain them inside different
configurations.
So, here either I can create a
configuration folder or I can create a
structure. I can even create a virtual
folder or I can create simply a
configuration, right? So, if you want to
create a configuration for uh different
projects, like so like project A
and then project B.
Okay, so we can do that. So, we can we
can have two different configurations
for two different projects.
And then inside that, I can have my own
parameters, right? So, I can have um a
project which is using the browser
Chrome.
And then for project B, I can create a
parameter uh called browser,
but uh they are using Firefox, right?
Similarly, I can create a list of
different configurations here, right?
So, I can create something called
synchronization timeout, right? So, this
could be different for different
projects.
So, for one, I can set it uh 3,000
and for other,
well, here I can create
and then I can set it to 6,000 because
maybe the synchronization is much more
for this particular application.
So, similarly, you can have uh these uh
created at uh project level. And then it
can be defined for each of the projects.
It can have the same configuration
parameters, but the values are
different, right?
So, these are basically used to
structure your test configuration
parameters from a specific point.
And then if you've got a very diverse
repository which has got multiple teams
and multiple requirements, um then it is
very easy to maintain your uh
configurations at this project level.
Now, how do you use this configurations,
right? So, for example, I am running
this uh parameters test case, okay? And
uh I want to use a particular
configuration for this particular test
case. So, what I can do is I can drag
this project A configuration directly
into this parameters, right?
Now, uh when you see this uh this
project A configuration has now been
inherited from here, okay? And it is
using a specific set of configuration
parameters like the browser, the
synchronization timeout. Now, this could
be different for different test cases.
So, you can pull your individual
configuration from this uh
configurations folder into your test
cases or into your folders or into
executions, right?
So, this is uh how you can make this
more configurable and easy to maintain
for different projects.
Now, the other thing which you can also
do is if you're an admin and if you
don't want um the other team members to
change this project level
configurations,
then you can set it to read only, right?
So, if you go into any particular
configuration like this project A,
you go into the properties and then you
have to just change this predefined
value to true.
Okay? So, once you do that, this will be
um read-only configuration.
It cannot be changed or it cannot be
deleted. It can be inherited, but it
cannot be modified, okay?
So, now uh once uh we have defined this
predefined property to true, uh if we go
ahead and use this in a particular test
case, right? So, if I pull this again
into this particular test case, which is
parameters,
you will see that
even if I go ahead and change this,
right? So, here it is set to Chrome,
and if I go into my test case,
it is set to Firefox or Edge, right?
I can change it here, okay, and I can
maybe save it,
but it's not going to change the
original configuration, right? So, it
will reflect it in my test case, so I
can modify it, and I can run my test
case,
but it is not going to change it in the
original configuration, right? So,
that's the point of setting this
predefined to true, so that nobody can
change the original configuration, which
is set at a project level, right? They
can change their individual test case,
but then it will only be applied in that
particular test case, not
in other test cases. So, that way the
maintenance becomes easier, because you
can maintain it at one place,
and you can have your own structure, and
then
the changes across test cases will not
reflect directly at this level. So, this
can be locked down to just admins, and
they can only manage this
configurations, which are at a project
level.
So, this is all about configurations,
what are the different test
configuration parameters which are
available in Tosca, how you can create
them, how you can use them,
how you can create configurations at a
project level, and then how you can
maintain them
across different projects or teams.